<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Software | Twig Technology]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/categories/software/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T07:44:23+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Enno Rehling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[E-Mail Encryption]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/24/email-encryption/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T11:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/24/email-encryption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is a depressing thought: public-key encryption was around when I was in
college in the mid-90&rsquo;s, and it&rsquo;s still not widely adopted. Instead, it&rsquo;s
considered &ldquo;too complicated for regular users&rdquo;, and none of the major vendors
of email solutions has made an attempt to integrate encryption into their
software.</p>

<p>As long as the NSA and Google read every one of my emails, I want to have a way
of preserving my privacy. I&rsquo;m writing these instructions in the hope that some
of the people I communicate will find it easier to use encryption when
communicating with me.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Using GnuPG with Thunderbird</h2>

<p>PGP, or &ldquo;Pretty Good Privacy&rdquo;, is a standard for email encryption developed in
1991, and remains the de-facto standard until today. The most popular
implementation of the PGP standard is the Gnu Privacy Guard (commonly
abbreviated as GnuPG or GPG). On your computer, you will need to install a <a href="http://www.gnupg.org/">GnuPG download</a> that matches your operating system.</p>

<p>To integrate GnuPG into Thunderbird, you will need to install the <a href="https://www.enigmail.net/">Enigmail extension</a>.</p>

<h2>Using APG on Android</h2>

<p>On Android, PGP is implemented in the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.thialfihar.android.apg">APG App</a> that I mentioned in my previous posting.</p>

<h2>Inline PGP vs. PGP/MIME</h2>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gmail With K-9, and an Identity Change]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/23/using-gmail-with-k9/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T20:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/23/using-gmail-with-k9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous article, I described how to set up Thunderbird for use with your
Gmail account. That solves my annoyances with the Gmail web interface, and
allows me to use PGP encryption in my emails, something I&rsquo;ll probably write a
post about later. However, I also have a series Android devices on which I also
read email, and the Gmail app on them has a few of the same problems, namely the
lack of encryption. How much does the NSA pay the major vendors so they don&rsquo;t
implement this, and make it harder on us?</p>

<p>In this article, I&rsquo;ll show you how to set up the free K-9 Mail app, and add
a new identity to it, so we can prepare our eventual exit from Gmail altogether.
You may not choose to do that yet, but I did.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Send in the K-9 team</h2>

<p>Before you install K-9, you should <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.thialfihar.android.apg">install
APG</a>.
It provides PGP encryption for Android, and for reasons I&rsquo;ve never understood,
K-9 insists that it be installed first if you want to use both of them together.
For now, forget that you did that, I&rsquo;m going to deal with encryption in a later
posting.</p>

<p>After that, install the K-9 Mail application on our phone. Get it from
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.fsck.k9">Google&rsquo;s Store</a>, or
Market, or whatever your phone calls it. These app are very undemanding, and
I&rsquo;ve installed them on anything from an old Froyo phone to the latest KitKat
tablet.</p>

<p>After you&rsquo;ve installed K-9, you&rsquo;ll have to configure it to use your Gmail
account. As with Thunderbird, you will need to create another
<a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/185833">application-specific
password</a> for this if you are
using two-factor authentication. You want to use a different one, so that if you
ever lose your phone, you can just revoke the password that it used and cut off
access to your email.</p>

<p>From the menu, choose &ldquo;add account&rdquo;, enter your full email address and the
password, and let the app find the incoming and outgoing server settings for
you. Just like with Thunderbird, this should happen automatically, so no
memorizing of host names or ports required. When all is done, you&rsquo;re prompted for
a name for the account and your own name, and taken to the account view. By
default, your account will be set up to not poll the inbox repeatedly, so you
might want to change the folder poll frequency in the settings to something like
every 15 minutes. Take a look around all the settings and consider what you want
your phone to be doing.</p>

<h2>New Identity</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m ultimately trying to get out of Gmail entirely, and I have a domain that&rsquo;s
hosted at netbeat with a catch-all email account on their POP3 mail server. It
would be cool if I could slowly migrate to an email address on that domain, but
I don&rsquo;t have the patience to set up my own IMAP server for it yet.</p>

<p>First step in this is to configure Gmail to fetch the emails from that domain.
I&rsquo;ve been doing this for a while now, and even though it means Google gets even
more data about me, it was worth it for their superior spam filtering.
Instruction on how to set up Gmail&rsquo;s Mail Fetcher can be found in Google&rsquo;s
support pages: <a href="https://support.google.com/mail/answer/21289">Centralize mail from different accounts with Mail
Fetcher</a>.</p>

<p>The one disadvantage of this setup is that email now takes longer to be
delivered, because on top of K-9&rsquo;s polling frequency, each message now has to
first go to my domain host&rsquo;s servers, and then gets picked up by Gmail on a
regular schedule (up to an hour), so you should take that article&rsquo;s advice
and set up direct forwarding, too. How you do that differs based on your domain
host, so you&rsquo;re on your own there. When I did it, it caused my emails to arrive
almost instantly.</p>

<p>Secondly, you&rsquo;ll want to be able to send emails through Google&rsquo;s servers from
your new email address. Again, this is documented in the Google support pages:
<a href="https://support.google.com/mail/answer/22370">Sending mail from a different
address</a></p>

<p>Once this works, you should have a drop-down in Gmail&rsquo;s web interface that lets
you choose which identity you want to send email from. By using your new
identity, you are slowly training everyone you communicate with that you&rsquo;ve got
a new address &ndash; the address will get collected into their address books. their
replies will be sent to it, etc. You may also want to add a signature to your
emails that explains your new address. Just make sure not to tell the spammers
:&ndash;)</p>

<p>Back to K-9: In the account settings, under &ldquo;Sending mail&rdquo;, select &ldquo;Manage
Identities&rdquo;, and from the menu choose &ldquo;New Identity&rdquo; to add your alternate email
address. Then long-press on the newly created identity and choose &ldquo;Move to top /
make default&rdquo;. K-9 will use this identity for all new messages, but in replies,
it will default to whatever address the email went to, and not switch. Don&rsquo;t
worry if that&rsquo;s confusing, you can always change whatever identity it chooses
from a drop-down at the top of the composition screen, for any message you
write.</p>

<p>Thunderbird has a similar mechanism for multiple identities, and you might want
to set it up there, too. Rather than describe it here, I&rsquo;ll just link the
<a href="http://kb.mozillazine.org/Mozilla_Suite_:_FAQs_:_Mail_Aliases">Mozilla Knowledge
Base</a> and hope
you&rsquo;ll figure it out for yourself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Gmail With Thunderbird]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/23/using-gmail-with-thunderbird/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T14:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/23/using-gmail-with-thunderbird</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have had it with Gmail. The web interface is becoming more and more
antagonistic every day, and it is my firmly help belief that Gmail is not email.
Back in the days, Gmail was a standards-compliant service built on IMAP and SMTP,
with a fancy web interface. A web interface that eventually became so usable, it
convinced me that I did not actually need a desktop email application any longer.
Those days are over. The new Compose, the inability to use it with a PGP browser
extension, the G+ integration, the hopeless top-posting and that new thing where
every attachment gets stored into Drive are all making me harken back to a
simpler time.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why stick with Gmail at all?</h2>

<p>It is tempting to make a radical departure and just set up my own mail service
on my own domain. And one day, that&rsquo;s what I intend to do, but not everyone can
do that, and I believe in taking incremental steps in the right direction. So
the first thing I&rsquo;m doing is getting rid of Gmail the web application, but I am
keeping Gmail the IMAP/SMTP service. I have had this email address for the last
10 years (I signed up November 11, 2004), and it&rsquo;s become impossible to just
stop using it overnight.</p>

<h2>Thunderbird is still the best.</h2>

<p>Unlike Microsoft and Google, the Mozilla Foundation seems to truly believe in
Internet standards and extensibility, and Thunderbird is still the best desktop
email software. It also exists on every major platform, so if I ever decide to
abandon Windows, it will still be wherever I go.</p>

<p>There is at this time no Thunderbird for Android or iOS, and I doubt that this
will happen anytime soon. However, other email software exists, and the Android
Gmail app is not as awful as the web application, so the mental trauma is not
quite as high.</p>

<h2>Thunderbird Setup</h2>

<p>Modern versions of Thunderbird (I am running 24.2) recognize a Gmail address in
their account wizard and they will configure the correct IMAP and SMTP server
for you, with the correct SSL/TLS settings. If you are using two-factor
authentication (you should!), then this is one of the cases where you need to
use an
<a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/185833">application-specific password</a> to access
your Google account. Tell Thunderbird to remember it. You are encrypting your
hard drive, right?</p>

<p>Next, we need to do some configuration that Thunderbird doesn&rsquo;t get right, in
order to work around some behavior of Gmail that isn&rsquo;t like other IMAP servers.
Go to the newly created account settings, and configure the following sections:</p>

<h3>Server Settings</h3>

<p>Gmail calls its IMAP folders &ldquo;labels&rdquo;, and there are two kinds, the ones that
you defined, and the canonical ones, like Drafts, Trash, Sent Mail, etc. These
canonical folders all live under the <em>Gmail</em> folder of the IMAP folder
hierarchy. In this next step, we want to prevent Thunderbird from creating its
own copy of those canonical folders, and tell it to use the ones that Gmail
provides.</p>

<pre><code>When I delete a message: (*) Just mark it as deleted
</code></pre>

<p>The Gmail server automatically manages its internal Trash folder, and you don&rsquo;t
need to explicitly move deleted messages there.</p>

<h3>Copies &amp; Folders</h3>

<pre><code>When sending messages, automatically [ ] Place a copy in:
</code></pre>

<p>Leave this unchecked. Gmail&rsquo;s servers will automatically place a copy of every
outgoing message into the <em>Sent Mail</em> folder, and making another copy will just
create duplicates, and it really messes up the witless Gmail web interface.</p>

<pre><code>Message Archives [ ] Keep messages archived in:
</code></pre>

<p>Leave this unchecked, too. Google&rsquo;s equivalent of the Archive folder is the All
Mail label, which stores all Mail that you&rsquo;ve ever seen, and Thunderbird&rsquo;s
&ldquo;Archive"command seems to be doing the right thing (as in, something other than
the "Delete&rdquo; command).</p>

<pre><code>(*) Keep message drafts in: (*) Other:
</code></pre>

<p>We want to keep drafts in the Gmail Draft folder, not on a local computer, so
from the &ldquo;Other&rdquo; drop-down, choose your Gmail account, and then the Gmail/Drafts
folder.</p>

<pre><code>(*) Keep message templates in: (*) "Templates" folder in Local Folders
</code></pre>

<p>I must admit I&rsquo;ve never used Templates. There is probably an argument for
storing them on your Gmail account, so they are shared between all your
installations, but Gmail doesn&rsquo;t have the concept of Templates, so you&rsquo;d have to
create a custom label for them.</p>

<h3>Composition &amp; Addressing</h3>

<pre><code>[ ] Compose Messages in HTML format
</code></pre>

<p>This is where it all began. People flaunting the internet mail standards. Do us
all a favor and don&rsquo;t perpetuate that nonsense. You&rsquo;ll also want to disable this
if you have installed PGP encryption, because those two don&rsquo;t play well together.</p>

<h3>Junk Settings</h3>

<pre><code>[ ] Enable adaptive junk controls for this account
</code></pre>

<p>We should not be needing spam filters, because Gmail is doing a pretty awesome
job at filtering out junk email. It&rsquo;s one of the major reasons why people love
it so much. Thunderbird&rsquo;s junk filters do not integrate with the server-side
filtering of Gmail, so it&rsquo;s better to leave everything in this section
unchecked.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[International Characters on a US Keyboard in Windows 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/23/international-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T14:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/12/23/international-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many programmers, I use a US keyboard layout instead of my native German
(or Scandinavian) keyboard. This makes programming easier, because I don’t need
to put my right hand into contortions to get at the keys for angle brackets,
curly braces, or the backslash, and I am able to use my coworkers’computers and
vice versa (except for those Dvorak types). But sometimes, I want to write a
letter home, and I need the Umlauts and all that other stuff. There are four
basic solutions to this, all of which don’t work for me, and the final one that
I use today (skip right to the end if that is all you want to see).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Windows language bar</h2>

<p>I could install three keyboard layouts, and switch between them with the Left
Alt + Shift macro, as the Windows designers intended. Personally, I hate this,
because it’s designed as a per-application setting, but my brain does not
remember per-application state. The Alt-Shift combo is one that I frequently hit
by accident, and the task bar indicator only shows you its state on hover, while
the floating version of the language bar is a huge eyesore.</p>

<h2>Key codes</h2>

<p>Windows allows you to key in characters by their code point. Alt + 132 is &auml;, for
example. I would have to learn 14 of these three-digit combinations, and they
only work on the numeric keypad. This is a serious impediment to typing speed,
and in fact it’s easier to remember and faster to type out the HTML entity for
each of them. Most laptops, and my FILCO keyboard, do not have a numeric keypad,
so that option is out for other reasons, too.</p>

<h2>AllChars</h2>

<p>For a very long time, I was a huge fan of
<a href="http://allchars.zwolnet.com/">AllChars</a>, which is a small program that runs in
the task bar and adds a &ldquo;compose&rdquo; key. So if you wanted to type an &auml;, you type
the sequence ESC &quot; a. Sadly, this little piece of open source magic stopped
working reliably with later versions of Windows, and it was causing very erratic
behavior, so I had to stop doing that.</p>

<h2>US-International keyboard layout</h2>

<p>There is a special version of the US English keyboard layout called United
States-International. You can install it from the Control Panel, just like you
would install a German or Norwegian layout. In this layout, international
(mostly Western European) characters are assigned to combinations of Right Alt +
character, with special characters roughly located in the vicinity of
similar-looking ASCII characters. &Auml; is Right-Alt + Q, for example.
Alternatively, you can compose keys, because a number of keys are &ldquo;dead keys&rdquo;:
typing ~ + n gives you &ntilde;. I don’t need those dead keys, they get in the way:
when trying to type an apostrophe, I need to type the ‘ followed by a space, or
I risk it being conjoined with the following character.</p>

<h2>International layout without dead keys</h2>

<p>Microsoft has published a tool that allows anyone to edit their own keyboard
layout, and there is a kind soul who felt the same way that I did about the dead
keys, and published his solution. This is the solution I use today, <a href="http://freeman2222.mywebcommunity.org/us-intnd.zip">United
States-International (no dead
keys)</a>. It behaves exactly
like a US keyboard, with the exception of the Right-Alt key being a modifier to
access the international characters. I have this set as my default keyboard
layout on all my Windows computers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solved: Irfanview icons.dll on Windows 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/06/30/irfanview-icons-dll/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-30T06:47:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/06/30/irfanview-icons-dll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have used <a href="http://www.irfanview.com">Irfanview</a> as my image viewer
for many, many years, and one thing that it does well is customize the
windows explorer icons for supported file types through an icons.dll
file. There is a good explanation of how to make this work <a href="http://emilio.fobby.net/features.php?g=1">at
emiliolab</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Windows 7</h2>

<p>There are two problems that I had with this explanation on Windows:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>you cannot write to anywhere inside C:\Program Files (x86)
without administrator permissions, so 7-zip fails to extract the
icons.dll to the Plugins directory. Extract the file to the desktop
instead and copy it manually.</p></li>
<li><p>Irfanview needs administrator permissions to set the icon for a
file type (it has to write to the registry). So in order to change the
preference, start Irfanview by right-clicking it, and select &ldquo;Run as
Administrator&rdquo;.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
