<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Raspberry Pi | Twig Technology]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/categories/raspberry-pi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T07:44:23+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Enno Rehling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BTSync, Dropbox Alternative]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/05/14/i-heart-btsync/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-14T08:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2013/05/14/i-heart-btsync</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dropbox is a revolutionary product. It has made it simple for anyone
to share files between computers, access those files from a phone,
automatically load photos from my phone onto my computer, and make it
easy to share files publicly. Who needs USB sticks anymore?</p>

<h2>Why would I even want to quit Dropbox?</h2>

<!-- more -->


<p>Dropbox comes with some strings attached that I don&rsquo;t like. There
is no client for my Raspberry Pi, for example. Every file I share is
also uploaded to the cloud, and while they score 4 out of 5 stars in
the <a href="https://www.eff.org/who-has-your-back-2013">EFF&rsquo;s privacy rankings</a>,
there is no technically enforced guarantee that my data isn&rsquo;t shared
with others. They have been in the news with
<a href="http://www.zdnet.com/dropbox-gets-hacked-again-7000001928/">security incidents</a>
that make it clear files on their service are not encrypted. In fact,
by the nature of how their software works, they cannot be.</p>

<h2>Bittorrent Sync (BTSync)</h2>

<p><a href="http://labs.bittorrent.com/experiments/sync.html">BTSync</a> is a software that sets up a private swarm of computers that
share folders between them, just like regular bittorrent clients share
the files defined in a torrent among them, except that changes in the
folder are synced, too. It&rsquo;s free, easy to set up, and secure by
design. There is no cloud server that keeps a copy of all my data, and
as long as at least one machine in the swarm is reachable, I can sync
my folder to a new machine. Folders are shared by exchanging a secret
key, a short alphanumeric string, and computers discover each other
either on the local LAN or over the internet.</p>

<p>BTSync can share multiple folders, anywhere in the file system (no
central Dropbox folder here), with different people. I can share the
baby pictures with Mom and Grandma, travel plans with the rest of my
group, music with the living room computer, and a public folder with
my web server, or any other combination.</p>

<h3>Example use: Hack The Future</h3>

<p>For Hack The Future, I have a folder of all the installers for
software that we mentor. It&rsquo;s shared between the loaner laptops we
have, but it&rsquo;s easy to share that folder with somebody else, and
rather than downloading big installers over a museum&rsquo;s slow internet
connection, the new machine will pull in everything from the local
network, with the existing computers sharing the load.</p>

<h3>Example use: Raspberry Pi</h3>

<p>I said earlier that my complaint about Dropbox was that there is no
client for my Raspberry Pi. BTSync has an ARM client, and I use it to
seed folders that I want to have access to at any time. The Pi is my
only &ldquo;always on&rdquo; machine, and takes over the role of the Dropbox cloud
servers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
