<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Algorithms | Twig Technology]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/categories/algorithms/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T07:44:23+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Enno Rehling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prefix Search, Part 3: More Fun With Tries]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2012/05/28/prefix-search/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-28T16:49:49+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2012/05/28/prefix-search</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post, I demonstrated that crit-bit trees are really fast. This time,
I want to talk a little bit about my specific implementation of these tries, and
some interesting applications you can use them for.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I also want to acknowledge some of the prior art that I looked at before
deciding to roll my own implementation. Professor Bernstein himself has written
an implementation himself for his portable qhasm assembler. But since it&rsquo;s part
of a larger software product, I didn&rsquo;t want to disentangle it. Adam Langley has
an implementation on <a href="https://github.com/agl/critbit">his github</a> with
some outstanding documentation that was very useful, but it only stores
zero-terminated strings, not arbitrary data. While I didn&rsquo;t read his code too
closely to keep my own implementation challenging, I did steal the clever
bit-mask trick from it.</p>

<h2>More Things To Do With Tries</h2>

<p>While they are really good at string lookup, what crit-bit trees are best at is
finding strings with a common prefix. I implemented two separate functions for
this:
<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='c'><span class='line'><span class="k">const</span> <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nf">cb_find</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">critbit_tree</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">cb</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">const</span> <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">size_t</span> <span class="n">keylen</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">cb_foreach</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">critbit_tree</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">cb</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">const</span> <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">size_t</span> <span class="n">keylen</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">match_cb</span><span class="p">)(</span><span class="k">const</span> <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">const</span> <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">size_t</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">void</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">data</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>
The first function is straightforward, it looks for an exact match of the first
<code>keylen</code> bytes of <code>key</code> in the given tree. The second function
calls the <code>match_cb</code> callback on every match, which is a much easier
pattern to implement than trying to return all matches. Where would you store
them? Dynamic memory allocation is right out, of course. I compromised a bit by
writing the <code>b_find_prefix</code> function, which takes a buffer supplied by
the caller, but beare that paging through the results by calling it repeatedly
is quadratic in complexity, so you shouldn&rsquo;t do that. It&rsquo;s really just a hack.</p>

<h2>Use As A Fast Key-Value Store</h2>

<p>One really nifty thing that I have been using this code for is as a fast
key-value store. You could insert a couple of strings like &ldquo;config_value=42&rdquo; in
the tree and look for the first match with the prefix &ldquo;config_value=&rdquo;. There are
two wrapper macros in critbit.h to simplify this, and being able to store data
other than zero-terminated strings means I am not limited to storing string
values. Here&rsquo;s some example code that shows their use:
<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='c'><span class='line'><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">42</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">char</span> <span class="n">buffer</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">20</span><span class="p">];</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">const</span> <span class="kt">char</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">key</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">ldquo</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">herpderp</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">rdquo</span><span class="p">;;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">void</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">match</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">size_t</span> <span class="n">len</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">len</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">cb_new_kv</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">strlen</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">buffer</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">cb_insert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">cb</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">buffer</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">len</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">cb_find_prefix</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">cb</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">strlen</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">match</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">cb_get_kv</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">match</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">sizeof</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">int</span><span class="p">));</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>
What these macros essentially do is this:</p>

<ol>
<li><code>cb_new_kv</code> creates a (key,0,value) string inside buffer.</li>
<li>Once you insert it, you can search for it by prefix-search for the key plus its zero-terminator.</li>
<li>Finally, use <code>cb_get_kv</code> to extract the value from the first match.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Testing</h2>

<p>I approached this project with a test-first attitude, writing tests before
writing the actual implementation, and fixing bugs until the tests passed. I
wrote almost as many lines of tests for this as I wrote actual code, and it
still wasn&rsquo;t enough &ndash; one or two small issues slipped through. Lots of pointers
and memory-pokery is always tricky, and I think this is one of those cases where
it should be undisputed that unit tests are just incredibly useful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prefix Search, Part 2: Crit-bit Trees]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2012/05/26/prefix-search/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T10:35:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2012/05/26/prefix-search</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The problem with the prefix search problem I described in my previous post is
that there is most likely no good data structure in your language to do this
with. There certainly isn&rsquo;t one in C. But the good news is that we get to build
our own! How often do we still get to write data structures from scratch in this
day and age? And when is it ever a good idea?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Of course, you should always try to go with the simplest thing that works: In my
case, that&rsquo;s building an array of your million strings, and to search for a
prefix, just strncmp each entry. We&rsquo;ll benchmark that, see how well it performs,
and use it as our baseline for a good implementation.</p>

<p>Have a look at the <a href="https://github.com/badgerman/critbit/blob/master/naive.c">naive
implementation</a> that I
wrote. Finding a needle in a haystack of a million strings takes almost no time
at all, but building the array takes a while, so I&rsquo;ll just do 1000 searches,
each for a single needle, in a set of a million strings, followed by 1000
searches for a prefix that occurs exactly 11 times:</p>

<pre><code>$ bin/naive -x 100 1m 111111
init: 0.30s
find: 0.82s
$ bin/naive -x 1000 1m 111111
init: 0.26s
find: 7.51s
</code></pre>

<p>8 ms per lookup may not sound like much, but it&rsquo;s actually not a very good time
at all. Excellent! We like this in a naive solution that we want to beat :&ndash;)</p>

<h2>Introducing crit-bit trees</h2>

<p>The data structure we want for this sort of thing is conventionally known as a
radix-tree or trie. I think that&rsquo;s either pronounced like <strong>try</strong> or
like <strong>tree</strong>, but either way it&rsquo;s really confusing. Also, it really helps
to think of the data we are operating on as a string of bits, not characters.
The specific type of trie that I decided to implement is from
<a href="http://cr.yp.to/critbit.html">this paper</a> by the talented Mr.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_J._Bernstein" title="Daniel J. Bernstein">djb</a>.</p>

<p>The general idea of this approach is that we have a binary tree, and if some of
our bit-strings have a common prefix x such that one string has a prefix of x0
and the other x1, then the tree shall contain a node where all the strings
beginning with x0 are found to the left of the node, and all strings starting
with x1 are found to the right.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s neat is taht we don&rsquo;t need a node for every possible bit position either,
but only for those where actual strings in or dataset diverge. To give an
example, if we had only two strings 0001001 and 0100100, (these start to differ
at the second bit), then we create an internal node in my tree that contains the
bit-position, and two child pointers which point at external, or leaf, nodes
that contain our two strings. To find a string in this, we follow a trail of
internal nodes from the root, check the bit position in our needle string, and
recurse down to the respective child node. Once we reach a leaf, we compare our
needle to the string stored here, because it&rsquo;s possible that our needle and the
stored string differ at other bits that we did not check on our way down.</p>

<p>Apart from being a data structure for key lookups, an interesting property of
tries is that all entries beginning with a particular substring are children of
the same node. That makes this data structure the perfect candidate for our
problem of prefix search. So, how fast is it? Actually, it&rsquo;s way too fast to
measure with just 100 searches, but we can do simple divisions, so let&rsquo;s do a
million lookups and prefix searches instead:</p>

<pre><code>$ bin/benchmark -x 1m 1m 111111
init: 0.62s
find: 0.25s
$ bin/benchmark -x 1m 1m 11111
init: 0.66s
find: 1.09s
</code></pre>

<p>250 nanoseconds per lookup, and a microsecond per prefix-search. That&rsquo;s a pretty
neat improvement of four orders of magnitude! In my next post, I am going to
talk a little bit about the actual implementation and interface. I have published
my source code on <a href="https://github.com/badgerman/critbit">github</a>.</p>

<h2>Some Thoughts</h2>

<ul>
<li>My dataset is pretty small. A million keys like this can probably fit into a
modern CPU&rsquo;s L2 cache if they are small enough. But trust me, the numbers are
only getting better when the dataset grows!</li>
<li>Each internal node is really small: I need two pointers, a word to store the
bit position (my implementation is excessive and uses size_t, plus a byte to
store a bit mask. You could go a little smaller at the cost of performance
and/or size limitations, but it&rsquo;s on the order of one or two dozen bytes. All
internal nodes are the same size, so you would want to pair this with a clever
memory allocator.</li>
<li>Initialization is somewhat slower, because creating the tree is more
complicated than just doing a couple of allocations. However, you could
conceivably store the final tree in a compact format on disk once it&rsquo;s
generated, and load it as a big chunk of memory, where you replace a pointer
to an internal node with an integer index into your array of internal nodes.</li>
<li>The crit-bit tree also allows fast deletion, which I haven&rsquo;t benchmarked,
mostly because I have nothing to compare it to.</li>
<li>All times are taken with clock() on a JoyentCloud VM. I have no idea what kind
of CPU that translates to.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prefix Search, Part 1: A Challenge!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2012/05/24/prefix-search/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-24T20:35:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2012/05/24/prefix-search</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Algorithms and data structures are fun. The other week, I had the chance to
implement something I needed for a project: Given a large set of strings, find
all the ones that begin with a given prefix. For example, say you have a phone
book, and you want to find all the people whose name starts with Joe. Or a large
list of IP addresses, and you want to find all the ones that start with 192.168.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This is a fun problem, because I don&rsquo;t think any popular programming languages
have good data structures to do this. Let me know if I&rsquo;m wrong, but I can&rsquo;t
think of a naive way to implement this in Javascript or with the STL in C++.</p>

<p>I wrote my own solution in C, based on a paper by D. J. Bernstein. It is super
fast, and has some neat additional properties that I want to write about, but
I&rsquo;ll save that for one of my next posts (have to get this post count up). I&rsquo;m
putting the resulting code on github for the world, but I&rsquo;ll give you a chance
to think about the problem before I spoil it ;&ndash;)</p>

<p>If you are tempted to write your own solution, here&rsquo;s a clever little benchmark
I came up with: Insert all the numbers from 0 to 999,999 into your data
structure (as strings), then find all the ones where the first character is a
&lsquo;1&rsquo;. You should get exactly 111,111 matches, and the entire process should
probably take less than a second.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Kata: Unrolled Linked List in C]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2011/04/24/code-kata-unrolled-linked-list-in-c/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-24T08:00:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.twigtechnology.com/blog/2011/04/24/code-kata-unrolled-linked-list-in-c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I needed a linked list for the umpteenth time, and
instead of going with the old (data, next) pairs, I decided I wanted
something a bit more efficient, like an [unrolled
linked list][<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unrolled_linked_list">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unrolled_linked_list</a>
&ldquo;Wikipedia&rdquo;). This also provided a good opportunity to use the
CuTest unit testing framework and do some test-first
development.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The result is rather nice, testing actually found a small bug,
despite the fact that I was sure can do linked lists in my sleep, and
I was so pleased with the performance characteristics (better cache
efficiency and far fewer allocations) that I replaced all the lists in
Eressea with it.</p>

<h2>Code Sample</h2>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='c'><span class='line'><span class="n">quicklist</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">em</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">q</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">em</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">ql</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">// insert element at index:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ql_insert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ql_insert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">bar</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">assert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql_get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">==</span><span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">assert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql_length</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">==</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">// push element at end, get indexed element:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">ql_push</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">baz</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">assert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql_get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">==</span><span class="n">baz</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">// iterate over list:</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">for</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">q</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">q</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">ql_advance</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">ql</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">printf</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;%p &quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ql_get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">q</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="p">));</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;/</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>
The code is on <a href="https://github.com/badgerman/quicklist">github</a> for you to
use as you please.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
